<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<clinical_study rank="14625">
  <!-- This xml conforms to an XML Schema at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.xsd
 and an XML DTD at:
    https://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/html/images/info/public.dtd -->
  <required_header>
    <download_date>ClinicalTrials.gov processed this data on April 13, 2016</download_date>
    <link_text>Link to the current ClinicalTrials.gov record.</link_text>
    <url>https://clinicaltrials.gov/show/NCT00279916</url>
  </required_header>
  <id_info>
    <org_study_id>103-04</org_study_id>
    <secondary_id>XRG5029C/4008</secondary_id>
    <nct_id>NCT00279916</nct_id>
  </id_info>
  <brief_title>Short Term Relief of Eustachian Tube Dysfunction and Serous Otitis Media Using Intranasal Steroid Sprays</brief_title>
  <official_title>Short Term Relief of Eustachian Tube Dysfunction and Serous Otitis Media Using Intranasal Steroid Sprays: a Randomized Placebo-controlled Study</official_title>
  <sponsors>
    <lead_sponsor>
      <agency>Mayo Clinic</agency>
      <agency_class>Other</agency_class>
    </lead_sponsor>
    <collaborator>
      <agency>Aventis Pharmaceuticals</agency>
      <agency_class>Industry</agency_class>
    </collaborator>
  </sponsors>
  <source>Mayo Clinic</source>
  <oversight_info>
    <authority>United States: Institutional Review Board</authority>
    <has_dmc>Yes</has_dmc>
  </oversight_info>
  <brief_summary>
    <textblock>
      We hypothesize that intranasal steroid application will have a beneficial therapeutic effect
      in adults with regard to resolution of SOM and/or NMEP as compared to placebo. We further
      hypothesize that the rate of spontaneous short-term resolution of OME in adults treated with
      placebo will be relatively low (minority of patients).
    </textblock>
  </brief_summary>
  <detailed_description>
    <textblock>
      The term serous otitis media (SOM) generally refers to an accumulation of fluid within the
      middle ear space in the absence of signs indicating acute infection. Other frequently
      encountered descriptions of this condition include otitis media with effusion, secretory
      otitis media, non-suppurative otitis media, mucoid otitis media, or &quot;glue ear.&quot; Commonly,
      OME results in a conductive hearing loss due to restriction of tympanic membrane mobility as
      well as alteration of the acoustic properties of the middle ear space and round window. In
      addition to hearing loss, adults with this condition may complain of aural fullness or have
      an increased risk of acquiring acute otitis media.

      Negative middle ear pressure is a relatively common finding in adults that often is a
      precursor to the development of SOM. At times, NMEP may be great enough to induce medial
      retraction of the tympanic membrane and/or draping over the ossicles—often referred to as
      tympanic membrane atelectasis. This condition may be seen with or without a middle ear
      effusion. As with SOM, NMEP also has its own unique effect on the acoustic properties of the
      middle ear resulting in conductive hearing loss. Retraction of the tympanic membrane may
      ultimately lead to the formation of middle ear adhesions (adhesive otitis media) and/or
      acquired cholesteatoma.

      Both SOM and NMEP are elements of a clinical spectrum that results, in part, from
      dysfunction of the eustachian tube. The properly functioning eustachian tube affords
      ventilation of the middle ear cavity that is necessary to prevent the development of a
      negative pressure gradient which results from middle ear mucosal gas absorption. In turn, as
      negative pressure develops within the middle ear, a serous transudate may form and the
      tympanic membrane may retract. Other functions of the eustachian tube include acting as an
      outlet for clearance of glandular secretions and/or debris into the nasopharynx as well as
      forming a protective barrier (when collapsed) from ascending nasopharyngeal pathogens or
      barotrauma.

      Eustachian tube dysfunction (ETD) in the setting of SOM and NMEP primarily refers to an
      absent or inadequate ability to open the eustachian tube. The most common cause of
      persistent ETD in adults is rhinitis (allergic rhinitis, vasomotor rhinitis, or mixed
      rhinitis). In some instances, it is hypothesized that the severity of rhinitis might be
      subclinical in terms of causing typical symptoms (rhinorrhea, nasal obstruction, anosmia),
      yet still of sufficient severity in the region of the eustachian tube orifice as to cause
      ETD. Most attempts at addressing ETD medically for patients with rhinitis have been aimed at
      decreasing mucosal swelling. Although many varied therapeutic interventions have been
      devised to treat ETD, no single therapy has been proven clearly efficacious and/or gained
      widespread acceptance.

      In 2001, van Heerbeek et al1 reviewed the results reported for many of these interventions
      in animal models and humans. Medical interventions reviewed included topical and aerosolized
      surfactant, systemic beta and alpha adrenoreceptor agonists (among other decongestants),
      systemic antihistamines, and other agents aimed at improving mucociliary function. Although
      some of these interventions (surfactant and decongestants) have shown positive effects in
      some studies, there remains a disagreement in results between various reports and, in
      particular, a lack of prospective randomized double-blind placebo-controlled studies. The
      authors concluded that there was not sufficient data to clearly support any particular
      therapy in humans at that time. Of particular note, a separate report by van Heerbeek also
      demonstrated no effect of single dose topical application of a nasal decongestant (alpha
      receptor agonist) on ETD in children in a randomized, double-blinded, placebo-controlled
      study using sophisticated measures of eustachian tube function.

      Surgical interventions aimed at treating ETD have included PE tube placement and/or
      adenoidectomy. Multiple studies have reported no improvement of underlying ETD after
      pressure-equalization tube placement—despite improvement or resolution of SOM and/or
      tympanic membrane atelectasis. In fact, some authors have reported worsened eustachian tube
      function following pressure-equalization tube placement. Studies relating to adenoidectomy
      have dealt with the pediatric population and, in general, have also failed to demonstrate an
      improvement in ETD.

      Recently, Silverstein reported preliminary results of a non-controlled study of direct
      application of dexamethasone to the tympanic-side orifice of the eustachian tube via a wick
      passed through a pressure-equalization tube. Data on this limited study of a small cohort of
      patients indicated a positive effect in terms of resolving patient complaints of aural
      fullness and eventually converting their tympanograms to type A.

      Some clinicians have suggested that nasal steroid sprays may have a role in dealing with ETD
      causing SOM and NMEP. Specific attempts to address the effect of nasal steroid application
      on ETD are very limited. Most studies that exist do indeed suggest a benefit in children,
      but have generally been too limited in scope to definitively demonstrate statistically
      significant benefits. To our knowledge, no such studies exist that deal with adult patients.
      We are only aware of 4 studies that address treatment of SOM with nasal steroids in
      children; we are aware of no studies that specifically deal with NMEP.

      In 1982, Shapiro studied 45 children with both allergic rhinitis and SOM prospectively to
      compare aerosolized nasal dexamethasone to placebo. Normal middle ear pressures were
      encountered more frequently in the group treated with dexamethasone at 1 and 2 week
      intervals suggesting a benefit in the short-term; no statistical significance was found
      between the two groups when the study ended at week 3. The authors concluded that
      aerosolized dexamethasone had some therapeutic efficacy, but recommended that treatment be
      limited to 2 weeks.

      That same year, Lildholdt and Korthol reported data on 70 children treated with either
      intranasal beclomethasone or placebo and found no statistical difference in resolution of
      effusion at 4 weeks. The authors concluded that there was no active therapeutic effect on
      the studied population.

      In 1998 Tracy evaluated the benefit of adding intranasal steroids to an oral antibiotic
      regimen vs oral antibiotics plus placebo vs oral antibiotics alone in a study group of 61
      children and found more frequent resolution of effusions as noted by otoscopy, tympanometry,
      and a symptom questionnaire with steroid therapy at 1 and 2 months. The benefit was also
      noted at 3 months but it did not reach statistical significance. The authors concluded that
      intranasal steroids might be a useful adjunct to prophylactic antibiotic therapy.

      Finally, in 2002, a similar study by Karlidag demonstrated an 8 week resolution rate of SOM
      in children of 39% on a regimen of antibiotics and nasal steroids as compared to a rate of
      24% with antibiotics alone and 5% with no treatment. Roughly 20 children were in each
      treatment arm. However, the study sample was too small to be of statistical significance.

      It should again be noted that these studies were all based on pediatric subjects. Many
      believe that the mechanics of ETD differs between children and adults. Given the variations
      in anatomy and other key immunologic factors between adults and children with SOM, it is
      difficult to know what application the above limited pediatric studies might have in an
      adult patient population.

      Newer intranasal steroid preparations are generally safe with relatively few side effects as
      demonstrated in large studies dealing with allergic rhinitis.

      Due to the lack of a single accepted medical intervention to deal with ETD and the general
      benign nature of this condition, it is common practice for some physicians to take a &quot;wait
      and see&quot; initial approach when this clinical entity is encountered in lieu of prescribing
      unproved medications. It is generally accepted that some patients with NMEP and/or SOM will
      undergo spontaneous resolution of symptoms, yet the exact resolution rates are not clearly
      defined.
    </textblock>
  </detailed_description>
  <overall_status>Completed</overall_status>
  <start_date>September 2005</start_date>
  <completion_date type="Actual">March 2009</completion_date>
  <primary_completion_date type="Actual">February 2009</primary_completion_date>
  <phase>Phase 3</phase>
  <study_type>Interventional</study_type>
  <study_design>Allocation: Randomized, Endpoint Classification: Efficacy Study, Intervention Model: Parallel Assignment, Masking: Double Blind (Subject, Caregiver, Investigator, Outcomes Assessor), Primary Purpose: Treatment</study_design>
  <primary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Normalization</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Type A tympanogram in both ears</description>
  </primary_outcome>
  <secondary_outcome>
    <measure>Complete Normalization, Including Treatment Failures</measure>
    <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
    <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
    <description>Type A tympanogram and not taking antibiotics, oral decongestants, nasal spray or combo</description>
  </secondary_outcome>
  <number_of_arms>2</number_of_arms>
  <enrollment type="Actual">146</enrollment>
  <condition>Otitis Media, Serous</condition>
  <condition>Negative Middle Ear Pressure</condition>
  <condition>Rhinitis</condition>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>TAA-AQ</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Active Comparator</arm_group_type>
    <description>Nasacort AQ nasal spray</description>
  </arm_group>
  <arm_group>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
    <arm_group_type>Sham Comparator</arm_group_type>
  </arm_group>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>triamcinolone acetonide</intervention_name>
    <description>2 metered sprays in each nostril daily (55 mcg/spray)</description>
    <arm_group_label>TAA-AQ</arm_group_label>
    <other_name>Nasacort AQ, Sanofi-Aventis</other_name>
  </intervention>
  <intervention>
    <intervention_type>Drug</intervention_type>
    <intervention_name>placebo nasal spray</intervention_name>
    <description>aqueous solution lacking triamcinolone, 2 metered sprays in each nostril daily</description>
    <arm_group_label>Placebo</arm_group_label>
  </intervention>
  <eligibility>
    <criteria>
      <textblock>
        Patients with serous otitis media and/or negative middle ear pressure will be considered
        for enrollment.
      </textblock>
    </criteria>
    <gender>Both</gender>
    <minimum_age>6 Years</minimum_age>
    <maximum_age>N/A</maximum_age>
    <healthy_volunteers>No</healthy_volunteers>
  </eligibility>
  <overall_official>
    <last_name>Laura J. Orvidas, M.D.</last_name>
    <role>Principal Investigator</role>
    <affiliation>Mayo Clinic</affiliation>
  </overall_official>
  <location>
    <facility>
      <name>Mayo Clinic</name>
      <address>
        <city>Rochester</city>
        <state>Minnesota</state>
        <zip>55905</zip>
        <country>United States</country>
      </address>
    </facility>
  </location>
  <location_countries>
    <country>United States</country>
  </location_countries>
  <verification_date>July 2011</verification_date>
  <lastchanged_date>July 20, 2011</lastchanged_date>
  <firstreceived_date>January 18, 2006</firstreceived_date>
  <firstreceived_results_date>July 20, 2011</firstreceived_results_date>
  <responsible_party>
    <name_title>Laura J Orvidas, MD</name_title>
    <organization>Mayo Clinic</organization>
  </responsible_party>
  <is_fda_regulated>Yes</is_fda_regulated>
  <is_section_801>Yes</is_section_801>
  <has_expanded_access>No</has_expanded_access>
  <condition_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Otitis</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Otitis Media</mesh_term>
  </condition_browse>
  <intervention_browse>
    <!-- CAUTION:  The following MeSH terms are assigned with an imperfect algorithm  -->
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone Acetonide</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone diacetate</mesh_term>
    <mesh_term>Triamcinolone hexacetonide</mesh_term>
  </intervention_browse>

  <clinical_results>

    <participant_flow>
      <recruitment_details>Enrollment from 11/15/2005 through 9/5/08</recruitment_details>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="P1">
          <title>Group 1 (Nasacort AQ Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered spray in each nostril once daily of aqueous triamcinolone acetonide</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="P2">
          <title>Group 2 (Placebo Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered sprays in eacy nostril daily of an aqueous solution that lacked triamcinolone</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <period_list>
        <period>
          <title>Overall Study</title>
          <milestone_list>
            <milestone>
              <title>STARTED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="45"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="46"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="38"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="41"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
            <milestone>
              <title>NOT COMPLETED</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="7"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="5"/>
              </participants_list>
            </milestone>
          </milestone_list>
          <drop_withdraw_reason_list>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Withdrawal by Subject</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="4"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="3"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
            <drop_withdraw_reason>
              <title>Lost to Follow-up</title>
              <participants_list>
                <participants group_id="P1" count="3"/>
                <participants group_id="P2" count="2"/>
              </participants_list>
            </drop_withdraw_reason>
          </drop_withdraw_reason_list>
        </period>
      </period_list>
    </participant_flow>

    <baseline>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="B1">
          <title>Group 1 (Nasacort AQ Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered spray in each nostril once daily of aqueous triamcinolone acetonide</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B2">
          <title>Group 2 (Placebo Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered sprays in eacy nostril daily of an aqueous solution that lacked triamcinolone</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="B3">
          <title>Total</title>
          <description>Total of all reporting groups</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <measure_list>
        <measure>
          <title>Number of Participants</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <category_list>
            <category>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="45"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="46"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="91"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
          </category_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>Participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <category_list>
            <category>
              <sub_title>&lt;=18 years</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="16"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="18"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="34"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
            <category>
              <sub_title>Between 18 and 65 years</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="18"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="12"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="30"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
            <category>
              <sub_title>&gt;=65 years</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="11"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="27"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
          </category_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Age</title>
          <units>years</units>
          <param>Mean</param>
          <dispersion>Standard Deviation</dispersion>
          <category_list>
            <category>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="41.4" spread="28.4"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="42.0" spread="30.8"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="41.7" spread="29.5"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
          </category_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Gender</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <category_list>
            <category>
              <sub_title>Female</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="30"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="46"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
            <category>
              <sub_title>Male</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="15"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="30"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="45"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
          </category_list>
        </measure>
        <measure>
          <title>Tympanogram type in worst ear</title>
          <units>participants</units>
          <param>Number</param>
          <category_list>
            <category>
              <sub_title>A</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="0"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="0"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="0"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
            <category>
              <sub_title>B</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="17"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="16"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="33"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
            <category>
              <sub_title>C</sub_title>
              <measurement_list>
                <measurement group_id="B1" value="28"/>
                <measurement group_id="B2" value="30"/>
                <measurement group_id="B3" value="58"/>
              </measurement_list>
            </category>
          </category_list>
        </measure>
      </measure_list>
    </baseline>

    <outcome_list>
      <outcome>
        <type>Primary</type>
        <title>Complete Normalization</title>
        <description>Type A tympanogram in both ears</description>
        <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
        <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
        <population>Number of participants based on those who completed the study ands who had a follow-up tympanogram</population>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Group 1 (Nasacort AQ Nasal Spray)</title>
            <description>2 metered spray in each nostril once daily of aqueous triamcinolone acetonide</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Group 2 (Placebo Nasal Spray)</title>
            <description>2 metered sprays in eacy nostril daily of an aqueous solution that lacked triamcinolone</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure_list>
          <measure>
            <title>Number of Participants</title>
            <units>participants</units>
            <param>Number</param>
            <category_list>
              <category>
                <measurement_list>
                  <measurement group_id="O1" value="37"/>
                  <measurement group_id="O2" value="37"/>
                </measurement_list>
              </category>
            </category_list>
          </measure>
          <measure>
            <title>Complete Normalization</title>
            <description>Type A tympanogram in both ears</description>
            <units>participants</units>
            <param>Number</param>
            <category_list>
              <category>
                <measurement_list>
                  <measurement group_id="O1" value="7"/>
                  <measurement group_id="O2" value="12"/>
                </measurement_list>
              </category>
            </category_list>
          </measure>
        </measure_list>
      </outcome>
      <outcome>
        <type>Secondary</type>
        <title>Complete Normalization, Including Treatment Failures</title>
        <description>Type A tympanogram and not taking antibiotics, oral decongestants, nasal spray or combo</description>
        <time_frame>6 weeks</time_frame>
        <safety_issue>No</safety_issue>
        <group_list>
          <group group_id="O1">
            <title>Group 1 (Nasacort AQ Nasal Spray)</title>
            <description>2 metered spray in each nostril once daily of aqueous triamcinolone acetonide</description>
          </group>
          <group group_id="O2">
            <title>Group 2 (Placebo Nasal Spray)</title>
            <description>2 metered sprays in eacy nostril daily of an aqueous solution that lacked triamcinolone</description>
          </group>
        </group_list>
        <measure_list>
          <measure>
            <title>Number of Participants</title>
            <units>participants</units>
            <param>Number</param>
            <category_list>
              <category>
                <measurement_list>
                  <measurement group_id="O1" value="37"/>
                  <measurement group_id="O2" value="37"/>
                </measurement_list>
              </category>
            </category_list>
          </measure>
          <measure>
            <title>Complete Normalization, Including Treatment Failures</title>
            <description>Type A tympanogram and not taking antibiotics, oral decongestants, nasal spray or combo</description>
            <units>participants</units>
            <param>Number</param>
            <category_list>
              <category>
                <measurement_list>
                  <measurement group_id="O1" value="5"/>
                  <measurement group_id="O2" value="9"/>
                </measurement_list>
              </category>
            </category_list>
          </measure>
        </measure_list>
      </outcome>
    </outcome_list>

    <reported_events>
      <group_list>
        <group group_id="E1">
          <title>Group 1 (Nasacort AQ Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered spray in each nostril once daily of aqueous triamcinolone acetonide</description>
        </group>
        <group group_id="E2">
          <title>Group 2 (Placebo Nasal Spray)</title>
          <description>2 metered sprays in eacy nostril daily of an aqueous solution that lacked triamcinolone</description>
        </group>
      </group_list>
      <serious_events>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, serious adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="41"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </serious_events>
      <other_events>
        <frequency_threshold>1</frequency_threshold>
        <category_list>
          <category>
            <title>Total</title>
            <event_list>
              <event>
                <sub_title>Total, other adverse events</sub_title>
                <counts group_id="E1" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="45"/>
                <counts group_id="E2" subjects_affected="0" subjects_at_risk="41"/>
              </event>
            </event_list>
          </category>
        </category_list>
      </other_events>
    </reported_events>

    <certain_agreements>
      <pi_employee>Principal Investigators are NOT employed by the organization sponsoring the study.</pi_employee>
      <restrictive_agreement>There is NOT an agreement between Principal Investigators and the Sponsor (or its agents) that restricts the PI's rights to discuss or publish trial results after the trial is completed. </restrictive_agreement>
    </certain_agreements>
    <point_of_contact>
      <name_or_title>Dr. Laura Orvidas</name_or_title>
      <organization>Mayo Clinic</organization>
      <phone>507-284-3410</phone>
      <email>orvidas.laura@mayo.edu</email>
    </point_of_contact>
  </clinical_results>
</clinical_study>
